TINA SRIVASTRAVA: So
now we're going to dive
into the flight environment.
All right.
So the first part is flying.
Actually, let me
just pause there.
Were there any other
questions about the charts
and the airspace?
OK, good.
They're kind of related
to the flight environment,
so feel free to jump in here.
All right.
So flying.
So there's a fair amount
of work that a pilot
is supposed to do-- is actually
required to do before they fly.
So you're supposed to become
familiar with information
that pertains to your flight.
In fact, it's a very
good idea to do so,
that's exactly how you
become a safe pilot.
So it's important to
understand information
related to your flight.
So there's not only the airport
that you're taking off from--
and when Phillip talks
about performance,
he'll talk about the length
of runway that's required,
but you also want to know
about alternate airports
along your route.
So if I'm flying
from here to Maine,
for example, there's a lot
of airports along the route,
I'd want to identify a
couple along the way,
understand what the weather
forecast is for those airports,
whether or not they have
fuel, those types of things
are very relevant to know.
You're also supposed to
understand how much-- so we
talked about-- so when you talk
about aircraft performance,
you'll understand what length
of runway you require in order
to land, and then
you want to make sure
that the airports
that you've identified
as alternate airports
along the way
have long enough
runways for you to land.
So let's talk about
some of the paperwork.
So there's this
acronym, ARROW, that's
supposed to help you
remember the types of things
that you're required to
have inside the airplane.
So there's an Airworthiness
Certificate, Registration.
If you're going on an
international flight,
you need a radio license.
It's actually
pretty easy to get.
So if you wanted to fly
from here to Canada,
you only have to pay $60
to get your radio license
and you can go fly to
Canada, so it's great.
And also the international
language of aviation
is English.
So even if you go to Montreal,
you don't have to learn French,
you can speak in English and
land there, so it's great.
So O is the Operating
Limitations,
those are displayed
in various ways,
such as your flight
manual and placards,
and we'll give you some
pictures of placards
so you see what those are.
And then Weight and
Balance information,
and we have a whole talk
just about calculating weight
and balance I think tomorrow.
So operating limitations.
So these are real restrictions
on the aircraft in terms
of what is the
maximum speed you can
fly with and without
your flaps extended,
and which kind of
procedures can you do.
And we talked about
certain aircraft
that you're allowed to do these
fancy aerobatic procedures
in and other aircraft where
that's not a good idea,
because if you really push
your aircraft to enter a spin,
it may be very difficult
to recover from it.
And so there are
different things--
so one is called the POH or
the Pilot's Operating Handbook,
and I have a POH over
here, and it has a lot
of great information in it.
So pretty much everything
Philip taught you
about aircraft systems as
is in this book as well.
It tells you about--
everything about your airplane's
systems, its requirements,
its restrictions, and how you
calculate that runway length
that you need to land and
your weight and balance,
all that information
is inside these books.
So this is an example of
some of those limitations
for an SR20 as an example--
we were talking about
Cirrus aircraft.
And so you can see, the
same types of numbers
that Philip was pointing out
before, the different V speeds.
And he had also talked about
these maneuverability limits
as well.
Minimum flight crew for a
lot of these small airplanes
is usually one, but some of
the very big, complex airplanes
and jet aircraft require
the co-pilot as well,
and some airplanes even require
another crew member as well.
So there are certain
aircraft instruments
that you require when you fly.
So they're called
equipment requirements.
So a VFR day, which is
Visual Flight Rules-- so
a nice sunny day, no
clouds, so you'll be doing
VFR your entire time getting
your private pilot's license
except if you do a couple
days of instrument training,
but the vast majority
of time, you're
talking about a VFR flight.
So what do you need, you need
some of those key instruments
we were just talking about--
your airspeed indicator,
your altimeter, a compass,
and then a couple of things
related to the engine.
So you understand about
the engine, its oil
pressure, temperature,
and you need
to know things about your fuel.
And a lot of them
have alternates,
you could measure your
fuel from different ways,
but somehow you must
have a fuel gauge
to know how much fuel you have.
You also need to have
anti-collision strobe
lights that kind go
off, and seat belts.
Who knows what an ELT is?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Emergency
locator transmitter?
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: That's right.
And so that-- it's an emergency
device that basically activates
when your aircraft-- if
your aircraft is under
duress and is
descending very rapidly,
it goes off and emits
your location out so
that people can come and find
your aircraft very quickly.
There are also some-- and these
numbers, by the way at the top,
in case it wasn't
clear, are regulations.
So they're FAA regulations.
So 91.105 is a regulation about
pilots sitting in their seat
when you're flying the airplane.
So for all practical purposes,
when you guys were flying,
you have to sit down and be
the pilot and fly the airplane.
This isn't like a
big commercial jet
we're going to get up
and start walking around,
so you need you need
to basically sit down.
Seat belts.
As a pilot in
command, you also get
to make the rules
for your flight.
So if you think you have some
kind of rowdy passengers,
you just tell them the rule
is you must wear your seat
belt at all times.
The actuality is that there are
certain times and restrictions
where it's required.
So taxi, takeoff,
landing is required
to wear your seat belt, but you
can extend that rule and say,
at all times you must
always wear your seat belt.
There's also an
interesting regulation
that says that passengers
can't interfere with the crew
members, but I will
point out that depending
on who your passengers
are, they may or may not
comply with that regulation.
We already talked about the
different altimeter settings.
So kind of-- it can be the
case that you-- instead
of being the perfect
condition of 29.92,
it might be the
case that you need
to adjust your altimeter
to that local setting.
So we talked about
ADS where you can
dial in the frequency
of the ADS and it
announces the
weather information
for a particular area.
They will provide
the setting that you
need to set in that window.
So they'll say 29.98 or whatever
is the altimeter setting.
Also, if you're flying
over a bunch of places
and you're talking to
air traffic control,
they will update you-- if they
hand you from one air traffic
controller to another
air traffic controller,
one of the first
things they'll tell
you is what is the altimeter
setting for that area
so that everybody is
adjusted and everybody
knows what altitude they're at.
So there's a little
knob on your dial,
and you turn it until
that window on the right
says the right number.
Now if that's not
available, you already
have some information, which
is the airport elevation.
So also on those things
being passed around,
for a given airport, it tells
you what the elevation is.
So for example, if you know
that the airport is at 100 feet
elevation, you can
just-- and you're
sitting on the ground in your
aircraft getting your airplane
set up before you take
off, then you know
that you're at that 100 feet.
So you can just keep turning
the dial until it says 100 feet,
and then that'll actually give
you the setting in the window.
There's some restriction--
yes, go ahead.
AUDIENCE: What if you're flying
into an uncontrolled airport
or you don't have
altimeter setting?
How do you [INAUDIBLE]?
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: So
that happens a lot.
So you can basically look
at the nearest airport
is probably the best way.
And those are the
times that you really
want to keep in mind what
Philip was talking about,
that if you are going from
a hot place to a cold place,
you want to keep in mind
that hey, I might actually
be descending even though
my altimeter says I'm not.
But in general, if you have a
local setting that's nearby,
you're pretty much good.
They don't vary dramatically
unless the weather's
changing a lot, in
which case you really
shouldn't be flying
because it means
there's a huge front coming in.
So here's an airport diagram.
A lot of information here,
but one thing-- so this
is actually Bedford.
And so you can see
a couple of things
you wouldn't see at other
places, such as the US Air
Force ramp.
That's not going to
be at other places.
But you basically see these
two intersecting black lines.
So those are the main runways.
And each runway
is bi-directional.
So on one side--
so it says-- the number's
very small right here next
to the mouse.
So 11.
So that's runway 11.
And then on the other
side it says 29.
So basically you land in one
direction, it's one number;
if you land in the other
direction, it's another number,
and that number is corresponding
to the heading of that runway.
And then you see a bunch
of lighter gray lines.
So those are the
different taxiways.
And there's all
kinds of stuff here.
I won't go through
everything, but one thing
that's really relevant
is this acronym here.
And it kind of
looks like a lasso.
What it's saying is,
the land and hold short.
So if you're given
an instruction-- so
when you have two
intersecting runways,
they might want to
keep up the efficiency.
They might want to have
you land while they
have another airplane taking
off on the other runway.
And so there is a line that
says that if you given a land
and hold short instruction,
that you're supposed
to land-- that you're
supposed to hold short,
you're not supposed to
cross the intersecting
runway because there's
traffic on that runway.
Thanks.
Did everyone get the iPad
had to look at the sectional?
OK, great.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: On the sectionals,
I was looking at the Hanscom
area, and I could
not see anything
indicating the Air Force Base
and getting special symbol.
Are there special symbols
for military sites
that do have aircraft
taking off and landing?
And can you explain
what they are?
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: Yeah.
So that's restricted
airports, for example.
So they have a different
color and different symbol
around them that would indicate
that they're a restricted
airport.
One thing that's
kind of interesting
is that even though Hanscom's
at an Air Force Base,
it doesn't have any
particular restrictions.
So you just get a
nice private airport
that you can land at that
has ginormously long runways,
so it's just a great
training airport.
So Philip, I just went ahead
into the flight environment.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Oh, OK.
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: So
taxiing in the wind.
So this is-- what do
I mean by taxiing?
So you must have heard of
this on commercial aircraft.
So this is when you get from--
in that case, the jet
bridge out to the runway.
But basically as you're driving
along the different roads
at the airport that
are not the runway--
the taxiways, as you're doing
that, there could be wind.
In general, as we
talked about with regard
to lift earlier in
the day, you know
you like having the
wind coming at you--
and we'll get into
performance and why
it's really bad if the wind's
coming from behind you.
But usually the wind will be
coming down the active runway.
They decide which
runway is active usually
by the wind direction.
So there's a lot
of wind going on,
and when you're
taxiing to the runway,
you're probably going
in different directions
with respect to the wind.
So one thing that's
important is to think about
while you're taxiing, you have
to make certain corrections
to your aircraft's controls--
so to the rudder
and to the ailerons
and the elevator at the back.
And so when you're
taxing on the ground,
your rudder is used to actually
make turns on the ground.
The ailerons and
the elevator need
to be turned in such a
direction that basically results
in your airplane
staying on the ground
and not inadvertently being
lifted up by a gust of air.
So this airplane
is what we would
call a tailwheel, because
there's a wheel back here
at the tail.
So it has two wheels up front
and a tailwheel in the back.
A tricycle gear airplane
would have one big wheel
up at the front and
then two wheels--
so three wheels total, but
instead of a tailwheel,
it has one wheel up front.
So in this case, a tricycle
wheel-- so not like this,
but with a wheel up
front, what you want to do
is if there's a quartering
tailwind-- so a wind
coming from behind you from the
back, you want to dive away.
So you want to turn
your ailerons away
and you want to push forward
to dive away from the wind.
And if the wind is coming
from the front, a headwind,
you want to actually go into
the wind with your aileron,
and you want your
elevator to be neutral.
So instead of pushing
in or pulling back,
you just want it to be neutral.
It doesn't matter as
much for heavy airplanes,
but for literal airplanes,
you can get bounced around.
And so it's slightly
different for a tailwheel,
so it's good to figure
out which type of airplane
you're training on
and get used to how
you would make those
corrections as you're taxiing.
There are a lot of runway
markings and taxiway markings.
One thing I would really
encourage you to do
is that the next time you're
on a commercial flight,
get a window seat and
look out the window,
and you can see all these
markings as you go along.
You might be able
to identify which
runway you're taking off on.
And so I won't go
through each of these,
the actual runway
is this red number.
So why are there two numbers?
Why do they have 15 and 33?
That's right, because
runways are bi-directional.
So depending on which way
you're taking off on it
or which way you're
landing on it,
it could be runway
1-5 or runway 1-3.
The yellow ones
are talking about--
there's a difference between
when you're on the runway
or on the taxiway versus it's an
arrow pointing to it somewhere
else.
So this sign is on the
one that you're on,
and this one is saying-- so
if you see this A like this,
it means you're
on taxiway alpha.
If you see it like
this with an arrow,
it's says that way
to taxiway bravo.
It's very important that you do
visual scanning-- so you really
look around for other airplanes.
So when we talk about
Visual Flight Rules, VFR,
which is the vast
majority of your time
on your private
pilot, you need to be
looking outside the airplane
to look for other airplanes
to avoid.
And it's unfortunate,
but actually,
most mid-air collisions occur
near airports in good weather.
So if they had been
looking out, they
could have seen the
other airplanes.
So when we're talking
about the pros and cons
of low wing and high
wing, I was very focused
on your visibility.
So where you're
looking in terms of you
want to clear before
you make any turn,
you want to look before you go.
In fact, Mark Nathanson, the FAA
examiner who's coming tomorrow,
that's probably the easiest
way to fail your FAA exam.
He'll tell you to do a maneuver
and you just start doing it.
Fail.
You have to first
clear the area,
you might even do
a clearing turn.
So turn in one direction
and turn the other way,
because you know your wings
are kind of obscuring you,
so that you can look
all the way around,
make sure there are no
aircraft in the vicinity,
and then perform your maneuvers.
But of course, you
can also talk to air
traffic control and other folks
to get traffic advisories.
They will tell you, hey,
there's an aircraft at your 3
o'clock 5 miles ahead of you.
Those types of things
are very helpful.
They're not always required,
but they're recommended.
So before we talk
about right of way,
I thought I would just
challenge you with a question.
Who do you think has
the right of way,
a blimp, an aircraft refueling
another aircraft, or a glider?
So we're just
going to do a poll.
So how many people for blimp?
We've got about 20
people for blimp.
OK.
How many people for aircraft
refueling another aircraft?
That was almost the same
number, 20 people on aircraft
refueling another aircraft.
How many people for glider?
OK, glider has the majority
of the classroom here.
So the majority of the
classroom wins, it's the glider.
And this is a very
complicated question.
Obviously you would never be
in a situation where a blimp,
an aircraft refueling
another aircraft,
and a glider all coming
together head-on, but the--
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Burning Man.
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: Yeah.
So the glider wins
because it is unpowered.
And so unpowered
aircraft have a priority
over all powered aircraft.
However, if you're in a
glider and you see a blimp,
you know those things
are slow, I really
suggest avoiding it anyway.
So there are a bunch
of right of way rules
that are all described
in FAR 91.113.
And so it basically talks
about the order of operations.
And kind of the
big things to know
is that if anybody is in
distress or has an emergency,
they usually just get
priority over everybody else.
Balloons can't really move
that much and they can't decide
where they're going,
so even if you
wanted to assert
right of way, they're
not going to be able to move.
But then it really
is aircraft that
are unpowered get the priority.
There's also-- if you have
multiple aircraft that are
of the same class--
so two airplanes, two powered
airplanes coming at each other,
how do you decide who
has the right of way?
So there are some situations
which is basically
that two aircraft
that are converging
that are of the same category,
the aircraft on the right
has the right of way.
So there are a couple of
figures that describe that.
So basically if two aircraft
craft are looking head-on,
then you both you both
move to the right.
It's good to have
that rule of thumb.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Going back
to the priority list,
what category would
blimp fall on?
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: The blimp
is a powered aircraft.
Yeah, it's very slowly
powered, but it is powered,
and so it is it
powered aircraft.
If I said balloon
instead of blimp,
then the balloon would have won.
Yeah.
The balloon-- sorry,
the blimp is also
frequently called an airship.
So the FAA question might refer
to the blimp as an airship.
OK.
So this was the right of way.
And then-- yes.
So one thing that alters it is
if you have an aircraft that's
landing and it's on final
approach to landing,
then it has the right
of way, really, to land.
So this is where we talked
about the balloon has
priority over all the
others, the glider
has priority over all--
over powered aircraft.
The airship or the
blimp has the priority
over all other powered aircraft.
And then if you're
towing or refueling,
then you have that
priority as well.
So this is a little diagram
that shows you that--
it's very unlikely that you will
encounter an aircraft refueling
another aircraft.
So one thing to know is also
just minimum safe altitudes.
So in general, you're
the pilot in command.
You need to ensure
the safety of yourself
and your plane and
your passengers.
So in order to do that,
the biggest consideration
is that you're flying at an
altitude that's safe enough
that if something went
wrong in your airplane,
you would be able
to land safely.
So it's always good, regardless
of where you're flying,
to keep an eye out on
where's the closest airport
or where's the closest
flat, clear field
that you could land in, and you
want to be at an altitude such
that if you had
an engine failure,
you could make it safely to
that place and land safely.
So that's why even
though technically
in some of this
Class Golf airspace,
you could be flying at
100 feet above the ground,
unless it's a very, very
flat desert where you could
land anywhere, it's not a good
idea if you can't safely land.
Over a congested
area, which we talked
about is that yellow
area on the sectional,
you have to be higher.
So the idea is just not
to be a nuisance when
one's very congested.
And then do you want to
talk to helicopters at all?
Helicopters can do
whatever they want
is the ultimate rule of thumb.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: Yeah.
So basically--
TINA SRIVASTRAVA:
Actually, your--
sorry, your mic is over here.
PHILIP GREENSPUN: I
don't need the mic,
because I'll get up here,
this is louder than the mic.
So basically with a helicopter,
just listen to the airplane.
It's OK to lose the
machine and yourself.
So you can fly over
downtown Boston
quite low as long as you can
always end up in the Charles
River, for example.
But you can't go below the--
there are no arbitrary numbers.
You would just say, well
look, I could auto-rotated
to the street, or I could have
auto-rotated into the river,
and I wouldn't have destroyed
somebody else's building
or car.
So that's the only
rule for helicopters.
Don't fly super low when
there's an FAA safety
inspector actually in
your helicopter with you.
That's a good rule of thumb
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: Another thing
that's very important that you
just--
you don't be
careless or reckless.
So you're not
supposed to endanger
people's lives or property.
We talked a little
bit about placards
and how they can have
restrictions on them.
So this is what we
mean by a placard.
So they're just things that
are fixed to your airplane,
and it has some instructions,
whatever it's talking about.
These in particular,
for example, some of the
never exceed speeds
are listed, when
you need to turn on a strobe
light is restrict-- is
indicated, for example.
So I think is really interesting
about dropping objects.
There isn't a rule that says
you can't throw stuff out
of your airplane, it just as
that you have to know what--
where what you're
throwing will land such
that it doesn't
damage any property.
So there's some interesting
pumpkin festivals around here
that in the October time frame,
they'll give you pumpkins
and you can throw pumpkins
outside your airplane
and try to hit a giant X
in the middle of a field,
and there's no rule
against it as long
as you don't damage
any property,
so it's kind of interesting.
Formation flight is
kind of cool, too.
Obviously you can't do anything
that would be hazardous,
but if you are in communication
with another pilot,
you decided in advance
that you wanted to do it,
you can do this.
So I actually had one
MIT flying club flight,
three airplanes that
were part of the fly-out
decided they wanted to do
this, including myself.
And so we had three airplanes,
and we were nowhere near
as close as these planes
are to each other,
but we were in constant
communication with each other
and we were watching
each other and it
was really cool to
kind of fly together,
and we actually
landed as a flight--
so instead of each having our
own tail number identified
to an airport when
we were landing,
we picked an airport with an
extremely long runway and tower
controller, and we said, we want
to land as a flight of three.
And so they give us
clearance and basically--
a Cessna doesn't require
that much space to land.
You like to have 3,000 feet,
but 2,000 feet is pretty good.
And so this was a runway that
was over 8,000 feet long.
So we had one person kind
of landing at the front,
one person in the back, and
the last person touched down
before the first
person left, so it's
kind of a formation flight.
Only do this if you're really
comfortable with doing it.
You could always decline
and say no, and make sure
that you are definitely
in communication,
very good weather,
and you only do this
if it is a safe thing to do.
You're in charge as
the pilot of command--
pilot in command, PIC
of deciding whether it's
a safe thing to do or not.
There are also restrictions
about aircraft speed,
and the joke here is that
if you're flying an SR-71,
you would actually
stall even at 250 knots,
so you can fly as fast
as you want pretty much.
OK, so landing at an airport.
We discussed a little bit about
the runways and the runway
headings.
And so I think it's--
just in terms of
how did they number
that runway-- so what
does runway 36 mean?
Well, it's really referring
to 360 or pointing north,
but it's rounded.
So in here, it was actually
358, but they rounded it up
to runway 36.
And every now and again
they update these,
so you might see an airport
change its heading number
because it's that
magnetic heading.
If there are more than one
runways that are parallel,
then they can say left.
So Runway 21 Left or Runway
21 Right or C for Center.
Or if they have four runways,
they'll usually just pretend
that one's at a slightly
different degree
than the other ones,
so that one side
will be Runway 6 Left and
6 Right and then 7 Left
and 7 Right, you know they're
all basically parallel.
So there are a lot of
different runway markings.
These kind of arrows here talk
about a displaced threshold.
So what are the
restrictions there?
So you can feel free to taxi
and take off on that space,
but you're not supposed to land.
So you're supposed to cross
that big solid white line
before you land right here.
So there are a ton of
different runway markings.
Again, I encourage
you, even when
you're on a commercial
flight, to keep
your head out the window looking
at all the different lines
that you see so you can
leave the runway threshold,
you can see the number of the
runway that's written there,
and then there are
different stripes that
indicate how far down you are--
1,000 feet, every 500
feet, for example.
We talked about the X.
What does the X mean?
AUDIENCE: Closed.
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: Closed.
Don't land there.
The runway is closed.
So all of these
are kind of defined
in the PHAK, the Pilot's
Handbook of Aeronautical
Knowledge.
So I would kind of refresh them.
Some of them were
not very common.
One thing here is that
windsocks, windsocks are great.
There are different
kinds of windsocks
that basically tells you
which direction the wind
is blowing in.
When it's a very windy
day or gusty day,
it's very important to look
at a windsock, because even
though it will tell you--
for example, if
you hear on the ADS
that the winds
are 10 gusting 25,
that means that the winds are
10 knots, but sometimes a gust
up to 25 knots.
And a gust can kind
of change direction.
So it's very important
to know this,
and so you might want to
be looking at a windsock
as you're coming in or as
you're leaving the runway,
and you want to know which
direction the wind's going
and how much is it
changing, moving about,
so that when you come in, you're
prepared for that as you land.
There are other types
of wind indicators
that are pretty uncommon.
I doubt that you'll
encounter them,
but we've shown them here.
There's also-- so
the best way to fly
is really looking out
the window and looking
at what the runway looks like.
It's the picture of the runway.
So look at it, see what it
looks like, that's the best way.
But there's some things
that might trip you up,
like if runways are wider or
narrower than you're used to
or longer or shorter
than you're used to, then
it might appear to be in a
different place than it is.
So it's always good to have
an indicator as a backup.
So there are different
glide-slope indicators.
So a VASI is one where there
are these four little lights--
you basically see
them as four lights.
And if you're too
low, they're red,
and if you're too high,
they're all white,
but if you're
right on them about
1,000 feet down the runway--
so you basically use
these as you're coming in,
but once you can really see the
runway out the window yourself,
you look out the
window, not at--
and you look at the runway,
not at the these glide-slope
indicators as you get close.
So another variation is a PAPI.
So I like to think, again,
with these memory things,
VASI I think verticals,
so that's why they're--
some are on top and
some at the bottom.
A PAPI is the same thing,
but it's horizontal.
There also apparently exists a
tri-color visual approach slope
indicator.
Almost no one uses this and
you probably will never see it.
Same with this one.
But they exist, supposedly.
OK, so we'll focus on things
you might actually hear.
So land and hold short.
So we just talked about this.
Who remembers what land
and hold short means?
Yes?
AUDIENCE: Land, but
don't cross the runway
until you're given permission.
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: Absolutely.
So you can land, but don't
cross the intersecting runway
unless you're given permission.
So land and hold short is
something that the air traffic
controller might ask
you to do, and they
might be really assertive about
it and they might tell you,
we have a lot of
traffic here, I need
you to land and hold short.
Regardless of how
assertively they
tell you that, you're the pilot
in command and you can just--
you can just say no and
they have to deal with it.
So especially if
you're a new pilot,
you're actually not
allowed to accept a land
and hold short instruction
as a student pilot.
So if you're a
student pilot, they
tell you to land and hold
short, you have to say no.
And the reason is that you
may not be very good at it
and you might take more runway
than you thought you were
going to take in order to land.
Do you have a question?
No?
OK.
And yeah.
So you also have to have
proper visibility in order
to accept this type of
restriction as well.
Yes?
AUDIENCE: What
happens if you accept?
Or do you have to go around?
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: It's OK to
accept you have to go around,
you just have to--
you do what's safe for
you first, for your plane,
and then you communicate that as
quickly as possible to the air
traffic controller.
If you-- as soon as
you know that you
might have to go
around, you need
to communicate that
so that they can
try to make sure that
there's no incident
with the other aircraft.
But generally, you don't
want to accept a land
and hold short
unless you're very
comfortable with
the environment,
it's a good weather
condition, you
have a good handle
of your aircraft,
your air speed's doing
what you want it to do,
and you feel comfortable
that you could actually
follow that guidance.
But of course, at
the end of the day,
you're the pilot in
command, and if it's
going to be unsafe to you and
your aircraft to make a landing
and you have to do a
go-around, you have to do that,
and you just need to communicate
as quickly as possible
to the air traffic controller.
So there's some light signals.
Again, no one's probably ever
encountered this in real life,
but supposedly if your
radio dies and you
need to communicate with the
tower, they have this light gun
and they can communicate
a bunch of information
to you via these signals.
They're great candidates
for FAA questions,
they're unlikely to be used in
reality, and a lot of people
have their checklist.
It has like a page
in the back that
has this because it's so
rare, people don't usually
commit this to memory.
So here's some more resources
for you to refer to.
All right, are
there any questions?
PHILIP GREENSPUN: I don't you
have questions in conjunction
with a coffee break.
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: All right.
So it's--
PHILIP GREENSPUN: I'm
up next, and I figured--
I already saw people
sleeping through my last one,
so I decided to get
two boxes of coffee.
TINA SRIVASTRAVA: All right.
It's 2:15, so we'll
start up again at 2:30.